<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Moment of Methods]]></title>
  <link href="http://korenmiklos.github.com/Moment-of-Methods/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://korenmiklos.github.com/Moment-of-Methods/"/>
  <updated>2012-09-07T17:20:28+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://korenmiklos.github.com/Moment-of-Methods/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Miklós Koren]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I learned from software developers]]></title>
    <link href="http://korenmiklos.github.com/Moment-of-Methods/blog/2012/09/07/what-i-learned-from-software-developers/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-07T17:19:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://korenmiklos.github.com/Moment-of-Methods/blog/2012/09/07/what-i-learned-from-software-developers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>What I learned from software developers</h1>

<p>Software developers are like us on many levels. They build abstract models to solve concrete problems. They write lots of code. They work in teams. They love to show off their work to the community.</p>

<p>But first, and foremost, they love to learn new stuff to become better at what they do. The sheer number of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_programming_languages_by_category">programming languages</a> out there is amazing. So, the real defining fearure of nerds is not that they don&#8217;t have a life. It&#8217;s that they have an insatiable hunger for knowledge and up-to-date skills. Sounds like the way academics like to describe themselves. Nerds are us.</p>

<p>I learned from software developers to never stop developing my craft. Mind you, there is a fine line between learning useful new tools and browsing the web to procrastinate. But if you are still using Word to write your papers, email to send your files, an HTML editor and FTP to update your website, an old EViews to run your regressions, or unwieldy Matlab codes to simulate your model, you should ask yourself whether it&#8217;s because these are the best tools for you (might be) or because you grew lazy learn something new (more likely).</p>

<p>Software developers have taught me how to</p>

<ul>
<li>collaborate more effectively (use version control)</li>
<li>build useful abstractions (how to think about data)</li>
<li>write better code (optimized for humans, not computers)</li>
</ul>


<p>I will write about each of these in more detail.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
